rutenbeck_resume.md 12/7/2022

Nathan E. Rutenbeck

nathan@stonesetfarm.com

About

I'm a data scientist with two years experience recruiting, training, and leading a team in model and pipeline development and ten years experience building and deploying statistical and machine learning models in a production environment.

I'm passionate about translating business objectives into data analytics pipelines and incorporating data analytics into business strategy.

My technical focus is on Bayesian learning, combining deep learning and Bayesian learning, and uncertainty and risk quantification.

My industry background is carbon offsets and forest ecology and management, but I'm interested in positions across a wide range of fields related to green technology, energy, ESG finance, climate change mitigation, environmental management, and AI ethics.

Experience

Data science

Natural Capital Exchange (Jan 2018 - Dec 2022)

- Piloted core development of continental-scale models of forest structure and disturbance
- Piloted core development of data engineering pipelines for model training and deployment
- Helped recruit, hire, train, and lead a world class team of data scientists and data engineers
- Served as senior team member guiding model and pipeline development to meet business goals
- Provided data science intelligence internally to support business strategy
- Assisted carbon offset methodology and program development

Self employed statistical consultant (Nov 2015 - Dec 2017)

- Conducted a project examining technology use in the classroom on global educational outcomes
- Conducted a project examining the influence of wind development on bird and bat populations

Natural Capital Exchange (Jan 2014 - Nov 2015)

- Developed software and machine learning models to conduct remote-sensing assisted forest inventory
- Built MLOps pipelines to deploy inventory models
- Conducted remote sensing assisted forest inventory sample design, data collection, and processing
- Executed project operations, report development, and client communications

Graduate Research Assistant, University of Maine (2013-2014)

Agriculture and forest management

rutenbeck_resume.md 12/7/2022

Stoneset Farm, Brooklin ME (2005 - 2012)

 Owner and operator of organic farm producing low-bush blueberries, mixed vegetables, cut flowers, pork, chicken, and lamb

Horsepower Farm, Penobscot ME (2004 - 2005)

• Teamster, logger, and farm worker

Skills and Knowledge

statistical and machine learning, MLOps, remote sensing and earth observation, carbon markets, forest biometrics, forest ecology and management, agriculture, social and environmental ethics

Tools

R, Python, bash, Stan, AWS, Azure, Docker, git, GitHub, Databricks, MLFlow, QGIS

Education

University of Maine (2012 - 2014) PhD, quantitative silviculture (unfinished)

Yale School of the Environment (2010 - 2012) MF - Quantitative silviculture

Yale Divinity School (2018 - 2012 MAR - Social and environmental ethics

Bard College Bachelor of Arts - Religion (1999 - 2003)

Awards

- Doris Duke Conservation Fellowship, Doris Duke Foundation (2011)
- Irma Brandeis Award, Bard College (2003)
- Book Award, Bard College (2003)

Peer-reviewed publications

 Nathan E. Rutenbeck, Brent R. Frey, Kristofer Covey, Graeme P. Berlyn, Oswald J. Schmitz, Bruce Conrad Larson, Mark S. Ashton. Influence of gap position and competition control on the leaf physiology of planted Picea glauca and natural regeneration of Populus tremuloides. Forest Ecology and Management. 2018 Sep 18.